<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Steven Laidlaw: Author</title>
    <link>/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Steven Laidlaw: Author</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 11:07:29 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing Again and Pulse Re-Edit</title>
      <link>/post/writing-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 11:07:29 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/writing-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s been a while since I&amp;rsquo;ve updated this blog, and I thought it was time to let you all know what&amp;rsquo;s been going on. Between my day job and family responsibilities I&amp;rsquo;ve been neglecting my writing for the past six months. What this means is that I&amp;rsquo;m super behind schedule when it comes to the Pulse sequel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bright side here is that I&amp;rsquo;ve recently rediscovered some time and have spent it doing a few things. First of all, anyone who owns an e-book copy of Pulse can now download an updated version with much better editing. I&amp;rsquo;m confident we&amp;rsquo;ve discovered most of the spelling and grammar mistakes, and so the book won&amp;rsquo;t be so jarring in places anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I&amp;rsquo;m writing and editing the sequel, Blink. I&amp;rsquo;m about a third of the way through, and barring any life-altering events I should be complete within the next three months or so. Not saying it will be released then, as I want to make sure it&amp;rsquo;s polished, but the first run at the manuscript will hopefully be complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So anyway, not much else to say, but thanks for those of you who&amp;rsquo;ve given me kind reviews, and I hope to bring you more content as soon as I can!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. I&amp;rsquo;ve also been thinking of doing a post on how I set up my ebooks and print editions using HTML and Markdown. If anyone would be interested in this then please let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new Licensing and Sharing Philosophy</title>
      <link>/post/licencing-sharing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 15:21:42 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/licencing-sharing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-love-reading&#34;&gt;I love reading.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an author I know thats probably a given, but I wanted to state it for the record. I. Love. Reading. I love it so much that I started writing. Writing is pretty hard, but it&amp;rsquo;s worth it to give something back to the world of reading that I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten so much from myself. But sometimes the writing world sucks. Marketing is a thing that exists. Getting your name out there. Building a brand. All the usual nonsense. You know what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sick of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, I know, woe is me. But this isn&amp;rsquo;t what I do for a living. This is a passion of mine. Something I love. Something I want to share with other people. Self-publishing has come a long way thanks to Amazon, and the internet has given us so many more opportunities to share the things we love with the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there has to be more. There has to be some way to make sure it&amp;rsquo;s about the art, and not about the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-rap-industry-or-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love-free-shit&#34;&gt;The rap industry, or how I learned to stop worrying and love free shit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to go off on a tangent for a moment, but stay with me because I think this is important. In the rap world almost all artists start out releasing mix-tapes. This isn&amp;rsquo;t exactly a secret, but what surprised me was that almost all established rappers still release mix-tapes even after they sell millions of albums. Usually they release more mix-tapes than they do official studio albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t help them in terms of sales directly, but it &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; help them spread their brand more and give back to the rap community itself (co-signing other up-and-coming artists, using beats they normally wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have the rights to, etc). The best part of this though is that they are doing it purely for the art. The sheer pleasure they get in releasing something they are proud of, and not something that a label has taken and chopped to pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LEvOcDxI734&#34;&gt;watching an interview with Donald Glover&lt;/a&gt; the other day and he spoke about not liking to be restricted. He likes being able to be a writer, an actor, a comedian, a rapper, and anything else he decides is worth his time pursuing. He spoke for a while about the art he makes, and why he does it, and I think it really goes to show how much he cares about the things he puts his heart and soul into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of philosophy really gets to the root of why people make art. The world is changing. The internet is making sharing easier. Just look at the indie EDM community explosion that&amp;rsquo;s taken place over the last few years. There is new stuff coming out so fast that I can&amp;rsquo;t keep up. It&amp;rsquo;s amazing. This is the world I want to live in. A world of pure creation without restriction. A world where corporations don&amp;rsquo;t decide who is the current thing. A world where we get to decide for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;creative-commons&#34;&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to licence all my current books under the &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;Creative Commons BY-NC-SA Licence&lt;/a&gt;. While that may seem complicated, it&amp;rsquo;s actually pretty simple and can be broken down into two main concepts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. You&amp;rsquo;re free to share my novel&lt;/em&gt;
Yep, that&amp;rsquo;s right. Make copies to give to your friends. Upload it to your favourite torrent tracker. Share it on Usenet. Hell post it up on your blog for all I care. You won&amp;rsquo;t be in trouble. It&amp;rsquo;s legal. In fact you&amp;rsquo;d be doing me a favour. Get out there. Share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. You&amp;rsquo;re free to modify the novel and use its content yourself, with conditions&lt;/em&gt;
Want to change the ending? Be my guest. Want to write fan-fiction? Go nuts. Want to make a free fan film? Best be hooking me up with the link once it&amp;rsquo;s posted to YouTube! The only thing here is that you cannot use any of it for commercial gain, and whatever you create also has to be under this licence. Also you have to give me credit for the original, and link back to it. Aside from that though, you&amp;rsquo;re good to get creating!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;so-when-is-this-all-happening-steven&#34;&gt;So when is this all happening, Steven?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now. If you buy my book now from Amazon it will have the old licence information in it, but I&amp;rsquo;ll be updating that as soon as I can. In the meantime, feel free to bypass Amazon and request a free copy for the book from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh yeah, by the way, I&amp;rsquo;m going to be giving away my book for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a completely original idea, and I have to thank &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slhuang.com/&#34;&gt;SL Huang&lt;/a&gt; and her novel &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slhuang.com/books/&#34;&gt;Zero Sum Game&lt;/a&gt; for letting me know that this kind of thing was possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know I said that this wasn&amp;rsquo;t something I do for a living, but that obviously doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be successful and make money. Heck if I can make a living from this then I would be able to dedicate more time to it. I have some ideas about making this viable that I&amp;rsquo;m not ready to share just yet until I iron out all the details, but until then feel free to get a copy of the novel from me and share it around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that&amp;rsquo;s how it&amp;rsquo;s going to be and for the foreseeable future this will be how I&amp;rsquo;m going to be giving back to the reading community. I hope you guys are ready for this journey. I know I&amp;rsquo;m excited to see where it leads.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is NaNoWriMo bad for writing?</title>
      <link>/post/nano-bad/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2016 15:18:39 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/nano-bad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; This is a blog post I wrote a couple years ago on another platform. I decided to port it here as I think it&amp;rsquo;s still relevant.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is NaNoWriMo?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you who don&amp;rsquo;t know, NaNoWriMo (usually shortened to NaNo) is the National Novel Writing Month. Held every year in November, the idea is that starting on the first you will start writing, and output as much as possible before the end of the month. The goal is to hit 50,000 words within this time, giving you a great start to writing and completing your first novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we are all on the same page, I can start with the problems that some people have with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen a lot of talk lately about how NaNo is a bad thing. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s tourism,&amp;rdquo; established writers will say. &amp;ldquo;It invites piles of trash in our inbox come December,&amp;rdquo; publishing houses will say. You will hear others complain of how these ‘non-writers&amp;rsquo; are trivialising what it takes to create a novel. That one month of spewing out the first garbage that comes to your mind is not what writing is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, to be honest, they are all right. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean people who want to participate in NaNo are wrong. I want to address each of these issues one at a time, to give each the attention they deserve and not just brush off what, in my opinion, are valid concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Three Issues&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NaNoWriMo is Tourism&lt;/em&gt;
I can understand the perspective that authors are coming from when they say this. To them, every month is NaNo. They spend their whole time writing, editing, proofing, and reading. Of course they do. This is their business. People who truly love writing will write, regardless of what month it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I agree that this is true, how does that detract from the concept of NaNo as a whole? The vast majority of people who are going to participate in this year&amp;rsquo;s event are not professional writers. They have their own lives; their own jobs; their own hassles to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These people are not all the same either. Some of them write a lot, but aren&amp;rsquo;t pro yet. Some would love to be a writer, but can never find the time. Some don&amp;rsquo;t even want to be writers, but feel they have a story worth telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing in common with all of these people is a lack of community. Established authors are part of a club. They have other authors they are friends with, who they can rely on to help them get through tough periods. First time writers don&amp;rsquo;t have that. Some lack the motivation, or willpower, or ability to get past that mountain of creating their first complete novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NaNo gives us that community. It gives us a network of people who, just like us, are going to stick it out for a month and try our hardest to be our best at something. A lot of them will fail, but that isn&amp;rsquo;t the point. The point is that it gives us a glimpse at what it is like to be in that club. That point when you feel like giving up, someone is there to catch you and help you get back onto your feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;December Slump for Editors&lt;/em&gt;
Now this is a complaint that I think has the most solid merit. Come the end of November, there will be a segment of people who will wrap up their zeroth draft and push it right out to every publishing house they can think of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a problem, but it is not a problem of NaNo. This is a problem of amateurs. These newbies to the writing world who think that whatever they put onto paper the first time is the best it is ever going to get. They don&amp;rsquo;t understand that a completed novel has been revised multiple times over. There is not one novel in existence (that I have ever heard of) that was written in one go. Everything has been torn apart at least once, and usually many more times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would happen regardless of any single event. NaNo just give us more of these people in a short period of time. It is an unavoidable part of getting non-writers to write a novel. This will happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But isn&amp;rsquo;t it worth it? Sure, you might be frustrated for a period of time, but there are also stories that aren&amp;rsquo;t submitted in December. These are now being revised. There are people who aren&amp;rsquo;t normally writers who are following through on the process. They are tearing it apart again and again, pushing forward to what will some day be a completed story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that story exists. Thanks to NaNo, that person who would never have written that story, has written that story. It will probably be awful, but it might be great. It might be the next best-seller. It might win the next Nobel Prize in Literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, to me, makes it worth it. Having to dig through a few piles of crap to find a nugget of gold is pretty much the reason we all love reading anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Month does not a Novel Make&lt;/em&gt;
This is essentially the same as the complaint above, but rooted more in pompousness than any actual business concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t say much more about this than I have already said above. Those that are going to dump, will. Those that are going to edit, will. It is what it is. It&amp;rsquo;s worth it. Your negative opinion does not change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main issue I take with this opinion is that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t help anything. It is purely there to bring down those that are trying to achieve something. We know that a novel isn&amp;rsquo;t written in a month. How does that make putting in effort a bad thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might sound a little defensive, but that is because I am. Writing a novel is hard as hell. It&amp;rsquo;s a struggle. It&amp;rsquo;s hard work. You have to pour yourself into something for an inordinate amount of time, that you aren&amp;rsquo;t even sure that other people are going to like. To have your work torn apart by others is a horrible, but necessary, experience that everyone who wants to publish something will go through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why tear those people down before they have even started? Don&amp;rsquo;t tell people how worthless they are when they are only just starting. If you do that, the worst thing imaginable might happen—they will give up. That is one book that could have changed the world that will now not be written. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So please, don&amp;rsquo;t do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand why these complaints exist. People love reading, and they are protective of it. They don&amp;rsquo;t want the art form diluted. They don&amp;rsquo;t want it to appear simplified. It is the attitude of ‘Not everyone can write a novel—let&amp;rsquo;s keep it that way&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the wrong way of thinking. Events like NaNo gave us The Night Circus. That book has won many awards, and it is modestly known for being written as part of NaNo. The difference that a lot of people seem to miss is that it was written over two of the events, and revised a hell of a lot in-between and after. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t released for years after the event for which it was written. But it is an amazing book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love reading. If you are reading this, I bet you love reading too. Is it not worth digging through a thousand &amp;lsquo;50 Shades&amp;rsquo; to get to one &amp;lsquo;Night Circus&amp;rsquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is, and I hope you feel the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things I learned Writing Pulse</title>
      <link>/post/five-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 15:14:20 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/five-things/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a regular reader of Chuck Wendig&amp;rsquo;s blog, &lt;a href=&#34;http://terribleminds.com/ramble/blog/&#34;&gt;TerribleMinds&lt;/a&gt;, and one of the things he does every now and then is gets guest posters to talk about what they learned while writing a novel. Because I&amp;rsquo;m not cool enough to appear on his blog yet I figured I&amp;rsquo;d steal his idea and write about it on my own blog anyway. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to go into publishing or design at all on this, and try to keep it purely about the writing. Those things can go into another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sooooooo here we go, the things I learned writing Pulse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to get it right on the first try&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pulse started as my attempt at NaNoWriMo in 2014. I&amp;rsquo;d written a lot of stuff for myself before then. I&amp;rsquo;d taken a course on grammar. I&amp;rsquo;d read two books on writing, and countless articles and blogs. I had written out a full synopsis for the story. I was ready to go. Then November hit, and I started writing. Two weeks in I&amp;rsquo;d hit 30,000 words, and while I was happy with my progress I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; happy with my story. At all. I hated it, in fact. I loved the idea, but the story itself just felt rushed to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided to restart the novel. Halfway through November I trashed all the chapters I&amp;rsquo;d written, did a rejig of the plan, and started writing again. I only made it to 10,000 words before giving up. It just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel right. I got depressed about it, and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to write. That was my first attempt at NaNo, and my first failure. I was dejected about the story, and didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I stopped writing that story. I sat down, planned out a different story, and a few weeks later started writing that one. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until a few months later in January that the solution to Pulse came to me. It&amp;rsquo;s not a single story. It&amp;rsquo;s too big for that, and there is no way I could give the proper perspective within only 100,000 words. That was the day I decided to split it out into a trilogy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I didn&amp;rsquo;t start right away. No, I did something else, which leads into the next thing I learned&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. A complete plan makes writing 1000x easier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past I&amp;rsquo;d written rough outlines, usually in the form of a one page synopsis. I thought this was preparing well. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t. This didn&amp;rsquo;t let me know how I was going to fill a book. This didn&amp;rsquo;t show me the ups and downs of the novel. This didn&amp;rsquo;t show me character arcs, or sub-plots. So what I did this time, instead of diving right in to the writing, was read. I read as many books as I could stomach on planning, but one in particular held my notice: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Story-Engineering-Larry-Brooks/dp/1582979987&#34;&gt;Story Engineering, by Larry Brooks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book has become my bible. While it&amp;rsquo;s quite wordy and has a few too many examples, the structure inside is the best thing I&amp;rsquo;ve come across as a tool for writing. I won&amp;rsquo;t go into details of the plan, you can find it elsewhere online or just get the book and learn it yourself. I also can&amp;rsquo;t guarantee it will change your writing as it did mine. All I can say is that it worked for me. Well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now my plans are thorough. They tell me everything my characters are doing, and why they are doing it. I can now get a lot more intimate with my characters, and know everything about them, and so can have them act in a more realistic and believable way when these obstacles are thrown in their path. I spent two weeks perfecting the plan for Pulse and then dove into the writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Alpha readers are amazing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing is better than people who read your novel. You need other eyes on it. You&amp;rsquo;re too close. You can&amp;rsquo;t be objective. We all get this in beta reading, but what about someone who is picking up your mistakes along the way? What if you&amp;rsquo;re heading in the wrong direction? This is where the alphas come in. Every time I would finish a chapter I would post it up on Google Docs and share the link with my two readers. Within a day or two I would have comments from both of them on what they thought about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was fantastic not just as a tool for understanding my story, but also &lt;em&gt;staying motivated to write!&lt;/em&gt; Nothing stirs the loins of the inner pen like people getting excited to read another chapter. Nothing. I owe the completion of the first draft of my novel to my two friends who did this for me. I doubt I would have been able to finish it without them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Let it rest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was done with the novel. Finally, for the first time in my life, I&amp;rsquo;d completed a full novel! I was officially (in my mind at least) an author. This was the first time I&amp;rsquo;d ever felt like I&amp;rsquo;d completed something that was worth it. I was ecstatic. I wanted to get it out there. I wanted people to read it. I started to look into publishing. Then I remembered what I&amp;rsquo;d read many, many times over in blogs and how-to books. Something I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to do. &lt;strong&gt;Take a break from it.&lt;/strong&gt; You can barely see the story any more you&amp;rsquo;re too close. You have to get away from it, and let it breathe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did. I put it aside, and started my next novel. I actually started a few novels, and dabbled writing a few chapters of each. Two months later, I went back and read what would become Pulse and&amp;hellip; well I&amp;rsquo;m not going to say it was awful, but I certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t love it as much as I had when I&amp;rsquo;d left it last. I got to experience it fresh, and I saw many flaws with it that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen when it had been my newborn baby. Now that it had grown a bit, I could see the ugly bits poking through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about a book though is that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to keep the ugly bits, so I dropped the first quarter of the book, dropped a few hanging chapters, merged a couple characters, and rejigged the final few chapters. The drop of the beginning of the story was the big part. 20,000 words to be precise. Gone. I then re-planned it how I wanted it to be and wrote hard. Now that I was sure what I wanted it to be it was much easier to burn through the words, and I managed to finish the new beginning (now a new 25,000 words) within only a few weeks. With these changes I also then had to go through the whole book again and change a lot of things to match the changes I&amp;rsquo;d made to the start. This was a great way to pick up any extra grammar and spelling mistakes too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Beta readers and line-edits are essential&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I was happy I needed new eyes on it. My alpha readers couldn&amp;rsquo;t do it because they were as close to the story as I was. They had seen it grow and change, and to be honest they were burned out. I needed someone new. Enter another friend (who, lucky for me, is an English teacher!) to read the story as a whole and even give me a rough line-edit. I was excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I didn&amp;rsquo;t anticipate was how awful my grammar and spelling were. I mean, I read all the time! I&amp;rsquo;d poured over Strunk and White! I&amp;rsquo;d researched obscure English! I subscribe to Grammar Girl! I&amp;rsquo;d taken a &lt;em&gt;damn course on grammar!!&lt;/em&gt; How the hell was I so bad at this? Apparently I was, which makes me glad I&amp;rsquo;d not decided to release the story right away. It would definitely not have been my best work, and am thankful I was given the chance to make it such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There we have it. A full year of writing from conception to completion. It started out as nothing more than an single-page synopsis, and became the story I love today, and all thanks to the things I learned along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically I can narrow it down to five simple things to keep in mind while writing your own novel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut yourself some slack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get people to read it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get new people to read it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this helped someone out there, and if so (or if you do it some other way) let me know in the comments below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PULSE Available Now!</title>
      <link>/post/pulse-available/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2015 15:07:49 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/pulse-available/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are live! My novel, PULSE, is now available for purchase through the Amazon store! Either click the link below to go to the US store, or navigate to your local amazon site and search my name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B018L5DJEO&#34;&gt;Get it now!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blurb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pickpocket Alexandra Murray has grown up in the bad part of New York City. She has spent her whole life learning that you can never rely on anyone but yourself. Since terrorist attacks gave the Military power to act on US soil, it has made life hard for someone who relies on stealing to survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is until her sixteenth birthday, when life as she knows it is changed forever. Will this be the chance that she has been looking for to make a new life for herself, or will misplaced trust and bad decisions see her lose her very freedom?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please let me know what you guys think via whichever method is easiest for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B018L5DJEO&#34;&gt;Again here is the link to Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time for a change</title>
      <link>/post/time-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2015 15:11:27 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/time-change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So for the past few weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing the new author thing. Built a website, got on Twitter, made a Facebook page, posted updates, and all that other shit. These were the things I needed to do (or so the web tells me) in order to become an author. I have to &amp;lsquo;become a brand&amp;rsquo;. Everything that I say and do should be to forward that brand. And I did it. I followed all the things that it said I should do, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been querying agents for the past few weeks for my debut novel. I&amp;rsquo;ve written and rewritten my synopsis, query, etc to make sure I&amp;rsquo;m putting my best foot forward. I&amp;rsquo;ve read hundreds of blog posts and articles detailing exactly what you should be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guess what? I hate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m probably not alone. I bet every writer hates doing that kind of stuff. Well, not every writer, there are likely people out there who fucking love it. Anyway what I&amp;rsquo;m trying to say is that I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m unique at all, or a special snowflake for writing this post. I&amp;rsquo;ll get to that later. Back to hating all the crap you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to do to be an author. Now I&amp;rsquo;m not saying these things are bad, or wrong, or that people shouldn&amp;rsquo;t do them. On the contrary. I think these things are awesome and helpful and everything that you need to do to get picked up by an agent or publisher, and become a successful author. What I &lt;strong&gt;am&lt;/strong&gt; saying is that, for me, it feels like I&amp;rsquo;ve been phoning it in. Nothing I&amp;rsquo;ve done (until starting this post) has felt organic or natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started thinking a few days ago about the people who inspire me more than anyone else. We all have favorite authors, bands, artists, and all that, but I was thinking about the people who really make me want to create art. All in all I came up with three people who inspire the shit out of me more than any others: Bo Burnham, Donald Glover, and Chuck Wendig. As an author, it&amp;rsquo;s probably dumb that only one other author made that list. It&amp;rsquo;s dumber when I confess that I&amp;rsquo;ve never read anything written by Wendig (I have two of his novels on my kindle and swear I&amp;rsquo;ll read them soon, but his writing isn&amp;rsquo;t what inspires me about him).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I had a think about what it was that really inspired me about those three people in particular:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bo Burnham&lt;/strong&gt; - Bo is a character and a human all rolled up into one. His shows are at once a carefully thought out act and a window into his heart and mind. He seamlessly switches between silly jokes, funny songs, meta discussion on his art form, and heart wrenching honesty. Bo is so self-aware that when you sit through his sets and see how everything he does it part of his soul being bared, you can&amp;rsquo;t help but fall in love with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Donald Glover&lt;/strong&gt; - Donald for me is the epitome of &amp;lsquo;doing it for myself&amp;rsquo;. The writer/actor/rapper/singer doesn&amp;rsquo;t really fit into the mold of others in his industry at his age, and he seems to float around and gravitate toward the project that most interests him at the time. His debut album is so honest it hurts, and I often find myself listening to his monologues and getting misty eyed. He is just the most honest and relatable guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chuck Wendig&lt;/strong&gt; - The reason I included Chuck here is that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t give a shit. He says what he wants, writes what he wants, isn&amp;rsquo;t afraid to be wrong, and isn&amp;rsquo;t afraid of &amp;lsquo;ruining his brand&amp;rsquo; by speaking his mind. Chuck is everything that I want to be, and is such an open guy who grows with his audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, you could say that Wendig not caring about his brand &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; his brand, but to be honest the same thing could be said about any of the guys on this list. Hell I&amp;rsquo;m yet to watch a Burnham show that doesn&amp;rsquo;t have him making fun of his own stage persona, while admitting that it&amp;rsquo;s all an act. His anti-act is his act. That&amp;rsquo;s kind of the point of all these guys. Glover, in his Gambino albums, raps about how the things he raps about are stupid, but they make him happy so who cares &amp;ndash; and isn&amp;rsquo;t life pretty much just stupid shit?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing about these guys that unifies them is their honesty. They know who they are, and they use that not only to drive them but it powers their creativity. And, to me, that is what makes me keep coming back to them and following their careers. That is what I want to be. And that is what led me to write this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this day forth I&amp;rsquo;m going to be as open and honest as possible. I want the love of the art to drive me, and not the desire to be rich, famous, etc. Of course if I can make a career out of this writing thing I&amp;rsquo;ll be over the fucking moon, but only insofar as that it will give me more time to write. I want to share my creations with you guys, and that means that from now I&amp;rsquo;ll be doing things a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I&amp;rsquo;m going to self publish by novel, Pulse. I&amp;rsquo;ve thought long and hard about the pros and cons of both ways of doing things, but when it comes right down to it I just want people to be able to read it. Nothing makes me happier than reading people&amp;rsquo;s responses to the things I put my characters through, be them negative or positive. That means more to me than having a &amp;lsquo;brand image&amp;rsquo; of being an author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I&amp;rsquo;m going to be open. I&amp;rsquo;m going to blog more, but it won&amp;rsquo;t always be about my writing. It will be whatever I feel passionate about that the time. I&amp;rsquo;m going to make mistakes along the way. I&amp;rsquo;m going to fuck up, say stupid shit, contradict myself, and probably change my mind. That&amp;rsquo;s fine. I&amp;rsquo;m human. It&amp;rsquo;s allowed. So call me on my bullshit! Anything that helps me grow as a person is always good in my book (hahaha, book, hahaha, I&amp;rsquo;m so funny).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway let me end this rant now, because it&amp;rsquo;s getting to be too long already. I&amp;rsquo;m going to finish up the cover for Pulse and then release that shit as soon as possible for you guys. All I ask in return is that you&amp;rsquo;re honest with me. If you hate something, let me know. If you love something, let me know (and other people too, cause I&amp;rsquo;m a whore for that attention as evidenced by this post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve made it this far, thanks. I&amp;rsquo;ll be updating my blog, Twitter, and Facebook, but this time I&amp;rsquo;ll be trying to keep it more honest and less &amp;lsquo;media friendly&amp;rsquo;. I hope you all enjoy this journey as much as I will.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Editing finished</title>
      <link>/post/editing-done/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2015 15:06:57 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/editing-done/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi guys, just a quick update here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editing is now finished with the help of my beta readers, and I have begun to query agents. Please remember that if my manuscript does get picked up by an agent that means the early 2016 time line is off. So is the cover probably, and maybe even the title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d rather it takes the extra time to put out the best book I can than have a rushed thing that I will hate in six months.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review - We Are All Completely Beside Ourselves</title>
      <link>/post/all-beside-ourselves/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2015 01:16:43 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/all-beside-ourselves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; We Are All Completely Beside Ourselves
&lt;strong&gt;Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Karen Joy Fowler&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem I have with most modern literary fiction is its inability to capture the sense of wonder that genre fiction does early on. Added to this is the general pretentiousness that most of the narrators have (usually due to the author&amp;rsquo;s opinion being shoved down your throat) and it leaves me unable to finish many of the literary novels that I start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So colour me surprised when I picked up this book and began reading. What started out as something that felt much like any other coming-of-age novel with broken families and stilted narrators quickly transformed into something a whole lot more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist: The story picks up when our narrator is in college. She used to have a sister her age, and an older brother, but now she has neither. Something about her sister was a little unusual, though. The book jumps through time to tell the story in a roundabout way, having our narrator finally come to terms with her childhood and the effect it had on who she is today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I implore you, if you&amp;rsquo;re interesting in reading this, don&amp;rsquo;t look up anything about the book online. Anything you read will spoil the surprise premise of the book, that has a much better impact when it blind sides you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing is superb, written by the same author of the Jane Austin Book Club. She knows how to tease information in such a way that will leave you unable to put the book down to keep tearing through the pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all I would give the story &lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; stars. I hope some of you enjoy reading this novel as much as I did, and will do when I re-read it in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About the Author</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.stevenlaidlaw.com/img/portrait.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;So Handsome&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;margin-right:24px;&#34; align=&#34;left&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steven Laidlaw was born in Western Australia and moved around a lot as a kid. As a teenager a drunk friend introduced him to Raymond Feist, and so began a quest to read as many fantasy novels as he could get his hands on (which, being in a kid rural Australia in the 90s, wasn&amp;rsquo;t very many). Naturally this led to attempting writing a few, but as is genrally the case with youth it never really progressed anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his teenage years, Steven moved to the big city of Perth (which, if anyone knows cities, really isn&amp;rsquo;t that big) to fulfill his dream of no longer living in the bush. This worked out rather well and therefore he needed to find some more dreams. Among following various other aspirations, he also began writing more in earnest. Awful stuff. Fan-fiction of the worst kind, and &amp;ldquo;original&amp;rdquo; fantasy fare that faithfully stuck to every predictable trope possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago he got serious about the writing part and started dedicating a lot more time to such. Over the course of two years he wrote, trashed, and re-wrote his debut novel, now known Pulse. He is still writing to this day, jumping between the Pulse sequel and fourteen other novel ideas that have been floating around in his head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find his latest updates on this site and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/steven_laidlaw&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. Or subscribe to my mailing list in the sidebar. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t spam, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t update more than once every two months. Promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;faq&#34;&gt;FAQ&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;When is your next book coming out?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the progress bar on the right? That&amp;rsquo;s about as close an estimate as you&amp;rsquo;re going to get I&amp;rsquo;m afraid. Usually that&amp;rsquo;s just the first draft, too, so when that hits 100% add another 6-18 months on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Will [insert_character] [insert_action]??&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nah. Well, probably. Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How many books set in the Pulse universe are you planning on writing?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At minimum three, as the trilogy is already completely planned out. Ideally six, as I have a second trilogy in mind, but we will have to see how it goes as I do have a few other standalone novels and series I plan on writing before getting back around to the second trilogy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can I ask you a question about the series, or writing in general?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can ask, but if it&amp;rsquo;s regarding something that is yet to be revealed I won&amp;rsquo;t be able to tell you. For anything else, and any writing questions, yes feel free to contact me! The best way is probably the &amp;lsquo;Contact&amp;rsquo; section of the site. I try to answer every email I get, but can&amp;rsquo;t promise it will be right away.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books</title>
      <link>/books/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/books/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-pulse-trilogy&#34;&gt;The Pulse Trilogy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;book-1-pulse&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Book 1 - Pulse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/pulse.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pulse Cover Image&#34; title=&#34;Pulse Cover Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pickpocket Alexandra Murray has grown up learning that you can never rely on anyone but yourself, and since terrorist attacks gave the military power to act on US soil, it&amp;rsquo;s made life hard for someone who relies on stealing to survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is until her sixteenth birthday when a horrible event triggers something within that changes her life forever. Will this be the change that she&amp;rsquo;s been looking for to make a new life for herself, or will misplaced trust and bad decisions see her lose her very freedom?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PULSE is the first in an exciting trilogy of action, adventure, romance, and super-powers. Lovers of modern fantasy, this is the book for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/B018L5DJEO&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;book-2-blink&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Book 2 - Blink&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/blink.png&#34; alt=&#34;Blink Cover Image&#34; title=&#34;Blink Cover Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexandra Murray is back and this time the stakes have been raised to their deadliest heights. After being on the run for months – from people that were once friends – she finds herself at the end of her rope and taking risks she would never have considered in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When she is almost captured she needs to decide what her freedom is really worth. Is the price getting too high to pay? And who is the mysterious man who helped her? Is he someone she can trust, or is it just another case of someone using her for their own agenda? Some risks just might be worth taking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BLINK is the second thrilling chapter in the Pulse trilogy. With more action, and new powers, this novel is perfect for anyone who loves modern urban fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Release date: TBA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;licensing-and-sharing-philosophy&#34;&gt;Licensing and Sharing Philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love reading. I know that&amp;rsquo;s probably a given, but I wanted to state it for the record. I. Love. Reading. I love it so much that I started writing. Writing is pretty hard, but it&amp;rsquo;s worth it to give something back to the world of reading that I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten so much from myself. To this end, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to licence all my current books under the &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;Creative Commons BY-NC-SA Licence&lt;/a&gt;. While that may seem complicated, it&amp;rsquo;s actually pretty simple and can be broken down into two main concepts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. You&amp;rsquo;re free to share my novel&lt;/em&gt;
Yep, that&amp;rsquo;s right. Make copies to give to your friends. Upload it to your favourite torrent tracker. Share it on Usenet. Hell post it up on your blog for all I care. You won&amp;rsquo;t be in trouble. It&amp;rsquo;s legal. In fact you&amp;rsquo;d be doing me a favour. Get out there. Share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. You&amp;rsquo;re free to modify the novel and use its content yourself, with conditions&lt;/em&gt;
Want to change the ending? Be my guest. Want to write fan-fiction? Go nuts. Want to make a free fan film? Best be hooking me up with the link once it&amp;rsquo;s posted to YouTube! The only thing here is that you cannot use any of it for commercial gain, and whatever you create also has to be under this licence. Also you have to give me credit for the original, and link back to it. Aside from that though, you&amp;rsquo;re good to get creating!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions feel free to contact me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>